<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<c:model
    xmlns:c="urn:webdetails/com/2012"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="urn:webdetails/com/2012 ../../schema/com_2012.xsd"
    xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


    <c:complexType name="DimensionsReader" space="pvc.options">
        <c:documentation>
            The options documentation class of a data dimensions reader.

            A dimensions reader is executed for each row of a
            data source to convert values of one or more columns
            into one or more atoms of certain dimensions.

            Together, a set of dimensions readers,
            are executed to fully convert
            each data source row into atoms of the defined dimension types.
            The atoms of each row are used to construct a datum.

            The mentioned data source row is called the <i>logical row</i>.
            Depending on the data source format (crosstab or relational),
            the actual rows carry different informaton.
            The <i>logical row</i> is a normalized view of each row of the data source,
            independent of its format.

            A dimensions reader can be configured in the following ways:
            <dl>
                <dt>specify <tt>names</tt> but not <tt>reader</tt></dt>
                <dd>
                    names are paired with any specified indexes, from left to right;
                    excess indexes feed dimensions whose name starts with the last specified name (a dimension group);
                    excess names are fed with the <i>non reserved</i>indexes
                    that follow the last specified index (or 0, if none);
                    indexes explicitly specified in dimensions readers are all
                    reserved beforehand
                </dd>
                <dt>specify <tt>indexes</tt> but not <tt>names</tt> and <tt>reader</tt></dt>
                <dd>
                    the specified indexes become reserved but are not read,
                    and so are effectively ignored
                </dd>
                <dt>specify both <tt>reader</tt> and <tt>names</tt></dt>
                <dd>
                    any specified indexes are reserved,
                    and no pairing is performed between these and the specified names;
                    the reader function may
                    read any column from the <i>logical row</i> and
                    return atoms from any of the dimensions specified in <tt>names</tt>;
                    atoms of stated dimensions, that are not returned,
                    result in a <i>null</i> value;
                    this form allows, for example,
                    splitting a value in the <i>logical row</i> into two dimensions.
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </c:documentation>

        <c:property name="names" type="string list(string)" category="General">
            <c:documentation>
                The name or names of the dimensions that the reader reads
                from each <i>logical row</i>.

                When the argument is a string, it can be a list of names,
                separated by the character ",".

                Only one dimensions reader or dimensions calculation can
                read or calculate a given dimension.
            </c:documentation>
        </c:property>

        <c:property name="indexes" type="number string list(number string)" category="General">
            <c:documentation>
                The index or indexes of the columns that the reader reads
                from each <i>logical row</i>.

                Only one dimensions reader can state that it reads a given index
                (although a dimensions reader function may sneek into any columns it likes).
            </c:documentation>
        </c:property>

        <c:property name="reader" type="pvc.options.varia.DimensionsReaderFun" category="General">
            <c:documentation>
                A dimensions reader function,
                reads the values of dimensions,
                for each <i>logical row</i>.

                When unspecified,
                one is created that performs a simple
                mapping between the specified names and indexes.

                A dimensions reader function can be specified
                to perform non-simple operations over the read columns,
                like the following:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        combine values from two or more columns into a single dimension,
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        split the value of one column into more than one dimension,
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        feed a dimension with correlated data read from an external data source.
                    </li>
                </ul>

                Dimensions reader functions need not be specifed to perform
                conversion or formatting operations of a single column.
                For those cases, the dimension type's
                <c:link to="pvc.options.DimensionType#converter" />
                and
                <c:link to="pvc.options.DimensionType#formatter" />
                are more appropriate.

                Also, when the value of a dimension
                is calculated from the value of other dimensions,
                a dimensions calculation may be more appropriate:
                see <c:link to="pvc.options.DimensionsCalculation"/>.

                The function may read columns whose indexes were not
                "reserved" in <tt>indexes</tt>.
                Those columns might be read by other readers,
                possibly default ones created by the translator.
            </c:documentation>
        </c:property>
    </c:complexType>

</c:model>
